So okay, so today's דף daf is י"ט. Yud-Tes. We start with
the new פרק. perek. We start on the very bottom of י"ח
עמוד ב Yud-Ches Amud-Beis
and we now shift finally into issues not relating to rain, but
still following the very sort of similar pattern in terms of other
reasons why someone would fast. Let's take a look. סדר תעניות אלו,
Seder ta'aniyot elu, this order of fasting, האומר ברביעה ראשונה, ha-omer birviyah
rishonah, are things said about the first rain, and if the first
rain is delayed. אבל צמחים ששנו, Aval tzmachim she-shanu,
if sprouts have changed, there's some actually blight or other type of
a thing that they are
that the way they're growing is different than they should be growing,
then that's like an immediate problem. Maybe there's an infestation. That's not
something that you can delay and go through a whole series of
three, three, seven. First יחידים, yechidim, then ציבור. tzibur. That's something that
there's something immediate that needs to be dealt with. What? ששנו She-shanu
mean changed?
I said changed. Like it changed from wheat to barley?
No, no, anyway, we're not dealing with macro things although we are
praying to God but still בדרך הטבע. bederech hateva. מתריעין עליהם מיד.
Matri'in aleihem miyad. Those types of things you מתריעין, matri'in, you blast
for, you know, call out for immediately. If you'll remember, there was
a debate whether that means שופר shofar blast or whether it means
עננו, Anenu, or does it mean both of them. But you do
presumably the whole special series of תפילות, tfillot, you know, accompanying with
that was assumed to be packaged with that was together the twenty-four
ברכות brachot of שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, maybe the taking of the
ארון aron out into the courtyard. So all of the special prayers
you respond immediately. Now, what about fasting? So let's take a look.
We'll see about the issue about fasting in a minute. This says
מתריעין עליהם מיד. matri'in aleihem miyad. וכן שפסקו גשמים בין גשם לגשם
ארבעים יום, V'chen shepasku geshamim bein geshem l'geshem arbaim yom,
if there is a forty-day even if it did rain at the
right time, or roughly at the right time, but then there's a
forty-day period where there was no rain, that also could be terrible
because then the plants start growing and then there's no rain and
maybe, you know, then it's even perhaps even more urgent. So in
that case מתריעין עליהם, matri'in aleihem, you also begin to do the
special תפילות tfillot מפני שהיא מכת בצורת, mipnei shehi makat batzoret, because
then that is a plague, a smiting of בצורת, batzoret, of famine,
although בצורת batzoret is a little bit less severe as we'll see
in the גמרא Gemara than רעב. ra'av. I don't know, how do
they translate בצורת batzoret there? Famine?
Drought. Okay,
so רעב ra'av and בצורת batzoret both, although רעב ra'av I guess
is only translated as famine,
both have to do with the lack of rain and therefore the
lack of crops, but בצורת batzoret is less severe than רעב. ra'av.
Okay, now by the way, if you think about it, the three,
three, and the seven, how much time was that? Three was about
a week and a half, another three is about another week and
a half, that's three weeks.
Seven
is four and a half weeks.
You start the second series
five, whatever, so we'll round up. Anyway, seven is like four and
a half weeks, right? So that's like about eight weeks. You round
up a little bit because whatever, nine weeks. So that's about, what
is that, about sixty days. So anyway, so
the starting of that, so that's to the end of that series,
but the starting of the seven, right, will come, remember there were
three periods. There was the three weeks of יחידים, yechidim, then right,
then the three weeks of the ציבור tzibur with the and the
starting in the daytime, three weeks of the ציבור tzibur starting at
the night time, and then the seven where you did the מתריעין
matri'in and the special תפילה. tfillah. So three, three, and three is
nine, which is about four and a half weeks, call it five
weeks, thirty-five days. My point being that there you got to the
מתריעין matri'in and the most severe after around thirty-five days. Here בין
גשם לגשם ארבעים יום, bein geshem l'geshem arbaim yom, if the same
period of time without rain, right, it's not like here because it
started raining it's a shorter period of time has passed and even
and it makes it worse. But nevertheless, even though it's already rained,
once there's that long of a gap, that makes it very severe
and very urgent. Yes?
If they do the three, three, and seven they will be fasting
on חנוכה. Chanukah.
Okay, that's a good point. I hadn't thought about that. What I
also have to say is not clear to me is when it
says עברו אלו ולא נענו avru elu v'lo na'anu or עברו אלו
ולא ירדו גשמים, avru elu v'lo yardu geshamim, right, and this isn't
discussed anywhere in the גמרא Gemara as far as I know, is
that ever does that mean immediately? Like we did our, you know,
Monday, Thursday, Monday, and we said okay, no rain, next Monday, Thursday,
Monday, you know, we're doing it again? You know, or you know,
that's what it sounds like. That's what it sounds like, you know,
to say well, let's give it a little time, see if our
תפילות tfillot work. It sounds like it's immediate. Anyway, it's interesting, I
hadn't figured out that it would always run into חנוכה, Chanukah, if
that's really true. Okay, anyway, I'll have to check the calendar now.
Yeah, I did.
Okay, all right, that's a good catch then. Okay, now ירדו לצמחים
אבל לא ירדו לאילן. Yardu l'tzmachim aval lo yardu l'ilan. Let's say
rain came down, enough rain for sprouts, meaning for crops, but not
enough for the trees, or not
appropriate. or for the trees, but it wasn't appropriate for the crops.
לזה ולזה *La-zeh u'la-zeh* was appropriate for both, אבל aval לא lo,
לבורות לשיחין ומערות *aval lo l'borot l'shichin u'm'arot*, but not enough for
the wells and the cisterns. In those cases, מתריעין עליהם מיד matri’in
aleihem mi-yad. *matri'in aleihem miyad*, you would do the shofar blast immediately.
Now that's a little bit interesting because we understand why if the
point being that it's not enough that it works for one, there's
a concern for the other, but what's the מיד miyad, *miyad*? Like
you know, even if everything is raining normally, just it wasn't enough
for the trees, it wasn't right for the trees, that would be
a מיד miyad. *miyad*? Or this maybe in the context of בין
גשם לגשם ארבעים יום *bein geshem l'geshem arba'im yom*, you know, so
maybe if it's in the context of forty days, it makes sense.
But anyway, this sounds pretty interesting. Not only is it enough to
do a מתריעין matriyin *matri'in*
when it's you know, when it's good for, when it's not good
for one even though it's good for the other, but there sounds
to be a מיד miyad *miyad* element here which is hard to
understand. Not sounds, there is a מיד *miyad* element here which is
hard to understand. וכן עיר Ir... שלא ירדו עליה גשמים *V'chen ir
shelo yaridu aleiha g'shamim*, or if there's a city that didn't have
rain even though another city did, דכתיב *dichtiv*, והמטרתי על עיר ir
אחת ועל עיר אחת לא אמטיר *V'himtarti al ir achat v'al ir
achat lo amtir*, חלקה אחת תמטיר *chelka achat tamtir*, right, we had
that, the Gemara did that דרשה *drasha* before. It could rain good
for one city and not for another, for a portion of a
city, so you might think, you know, that if the surrounding cities
have the rain they need, it's not such a big deal, you'll
just buy stuff from the surrounding cities. The Mishnah goes on and
says, nevertheless, top of י"ט עמוד א' *Yud Tet Amud Aleph*, אותה
העיר מתענה ומתרעת *Ota ha-ir mit'ana u'matra'at*, that city fasts and does
the blasts, וכל סביבותיה *v'chol svivotiah*, and all around it, מתענות ולא
מתריעות *mit'anot v'lo matriot*, do the fasts without the blasts. Tough to
distinguish, but okay. Anyway, do the fasts without the special תפילות Tefillot.
*tfilot*. Okay, רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva's אומר מתריעות ולא מתענות Omer matriot
velo mitanot, *Rabbi Akiva omer matriot v'lo mit'anot*. No, they only do
the special תפילות tefillot. *tfilot*, the surrounding cities, but they don't do
the fasting. So there's a question of the implication for the surrounding
cities, but we should just take a pause here to note that
in the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma, *Tana Kamma* the idea and this
makes complete sense to be assumed that that was the position at
the beginning of the Mishnah, right, the first response is fasting, and
only later more intensified response is not only are we fasting, we're
also doing this very radical sort of new תפילה Tefilla, *tfila* service,
right? מתריעות *Matriot* was at the end of the process, at the
seven. So presumably the whole point in the beginning of the Mishnah
of מתריעות מיד *matriot miyad*, you know, מתריעין עליהם matrin aleihem, מיד
*matri'in aleihem miyad* had two חידושים chiddushim *chidushim*, I mean or well,
or maybe it was the whole, or the way you'd call it
one point, but it was (a) the response is immediate, okay, and
(b) the response is not just, is the most extreme response, meaning
the תפילות tefillot *tfilot*, but obviously if you're doing the new תפילות
tefillot *tfilot* that includes everything that comes before the תפילות tefillot *tfilot*,
meaning the fasts. So presumably now we're even talking about here you
start at the end, you start with the full package, with the
fasts and with the תפילות tefillot. *tfilot*. Now we're getting to an
interesting position of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* who imagines that
you can have
the and therefore in some circumstances you're only going to do the
half package, you're only going to do the תעניות ta'aniyot *ta'aniyot* without
the תפילות tefillot *tfilot*, the surrounding cities, but you do get a
very interesting position of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* who seems,
who says that you can have the תפילות tefillot, *tfilot* without the
תעניות *ta'aniyot*. Now again, presumably he is not saying that in the
beginning of the Mishnah. Presumably in the beginning of the Mishnah everybody
agrees that the point is the full package. If you have a
tragedy that's impending, then obviously you do the full package. Why would
you do half of it? So that's the beginning of the Mishnah.
But here at the end you do have an interesting position of
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that says you just do the תפילות tefillot
*tfilot* and not the תעניות *ta'aniyot* for the surrounding cities. Not so
clear what this is about. Why would the surrounding cities do it
at all? So if you look at, it could just be an
issue of a type of עמו אנכי בצרה *imo anochi b'tzara* of
then, but then why would it be like limited to the surrounding
cities? So if you look at the רש"י Rashi *Rashi* here, the
pseudo-Rashi he says, מתריעות *matriot*, רש"י *Rashi* says like הכי גרסינן *hachi
garsinan*, and we'll do the top line, אותה העיר מתענה ומתרעת וכל
סביבותיה מתענות ולא מתריעות vechol svivoteiha mitanot velo matriot, *ota ha-ir mit'ana
u'matra'at v'chol svivotiah mit'anot v'lo matriot*, ולפיכך מתענות שאותה העיר שלא ירדו
עליה גשמים צריכה לקנות תבואה באותה העיר ויהיה בו ברעב *u'l'fichach mit'anot
she'ota ha-ir shelo yaridu aleiha g'shamim tzricha liknot tvua b'ota ha-ir v'yihiyeh
bo b'ra'av*. That there is something that impacts the, I mean you
could have said that city should be very happy because then they'll
get to have a, you know, raise their prices or something, but
okay, we won't be so callous. So there is here an impact
to the region. If a certain area is, has a real famine,
you know, even if everybody else is doing good, it means that
there's going to be scarcity for everyone or it's going to have
some larger impact on the region and therefore the other surrounding cities
participate in it. So with that in mind, what would be the
idea of the מתריעות ולא מתענות *matriot v'lo mit'anot* is interesting for
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* because again as we've been saying, מתריעות *matriot*
is usually the higher level. But one could imagine and if there's
a possibility that hey, maybe if we had to choose between the
two our תפילות tefillot *tfilot* are more impactful than our תענית Taanit
*ta'anit*, then why didn't we have the reverse order earlier, right? What
is the idea of having here the תפילה Tefilla *tfila* without the
תענית Taanit *ta'anit*? So what I would suggest in רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* is that the תענית Taanit is a reflection of the suffering
or an intensification of the suffering that you are already enduring, or
that you are and at and you're saying God you have not
given us rain, we are so suffering as a result, and the
תענית Taanit? just really brings to the forth, the fore, the the
intensity of the suffering. Look, look how physically suffering we are, we're
expressing it right now through the fact we're not even eating food
the whole day and we're fasting and we're miserable and so on.
So it's an intensification and a greater expression of the actual suffering
you're already undergoing. Whereas the surrounding cities aren't undergoing any suffering. תענית
Taanit would be an inappropriate expression for them. They could have תפילה,
Tefilla right, which is a way of praying for something that they're
concerned about, right? They're concerned about the future, they're concerned about how
this might come to impact them. But since it's so far not
about them, it's about someone else, right? So maybe the תענית Taanit.
is not the proper expression. So that's a just speculation here, but
רבי עקיבא's position is interesting because until now the תפילה Tefilla always
was this extreme תפילה Tefilla was always stage two, right? And that's
consistent certainly the implication of the beginning of the משנה, Mishna, the
position of the חכמים. Chachamim. So why would a surrounding city do
תפילה tefillah without without תענית? taanit So I do think it does
have something to do with the fact according to רבי עקיבא that
it is not personal about them. Okay, let's take a look now
as it continues. וכן עיר שיש בה דבר או מפולת, Vechein ir
sheyeish bah dever o mapolet,
if a city has pestilence or מפולת, mapolet, or some type of
an issue with falling walls, falling structures, אותה עיר מתענה ומתרעת, otah
ir mitanah umatra'at,
that city does the whole package, וכל סביבותיה מתענות ולא מתריעות,
and the surrounding cities do the תענית taanit? but not to the
point of these greater these greater תפילות. tefillot And רבי עקיבא again
says the interesting reverse position. אומר מתריעות ולא מתענות, no they do
the more extreme תפילה tefillah but they do not do תענית. taanit
Now again not exactly clear, but but one can speculate what the
relevance is. Like just because the walls of one city are falling
down and they've got, how does that, they haven't been good at
their upkeep, what does that affect us? But I mean if there's
a medical emergency there and a lot of people are dying and
injured or whatever, that could have an impact on the surrounding regions
as well. The need for doctors and and the other types of
sort of ways in which in which those demands will make will
make demands on the surrounding cities. But again not a hundred percent
clear which are the ones that impact the surrounding cities, which are
the ones that are identified and which are the ones that are
not, yes.
Wouldn't collapsing buildings be most likely from an earthquake? That's interesting. And
when would you start? One pothole, two potholes, three potholes?
It's an interesting question.
And earthquakes are often followed by successive earthquakes.
That's interesting, maybe.
And ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael has been plagued by earthquakes
for
millennia.
Interesting. Although one does wonder because in משנה ברכות Mishna Berachot they'd
have a way of referring to earthquakes, right, when they deal with
the ברכות Berachot that you make. But that's interesting. Okay, that's a
nice explanation. All right,
now move on. I, איזהו דבר? eizehu dever? עיר...
what would be an example of pestilence? How would you measure like
it's just not like a few people have died, what makes you
think that there's actually a plague of pestilence going on here? By
the way, what is that דבר? dever? That's like some type of
is it is it like when they say it was is it
I mean do we know what the ancients meant when they what
how we would medically categorize what דבר dever is, scientifically, what pestilence
was? What was the black plague?
It's a bacterial infection and transmitted by fleas.
Aha, so probably what some what these דבר... dever...
and there was a horrific, the first really horrific example of it
was actually in the sixth century
CE, about the time that the תלמוד Talmud would have been completed.
Aha. Well, this is the משנה Mishna though. All right, anyway, presumably
it is some, some, anyway, whatever it is, plague. What would be
a way of measuring it? עיר המוציאה חמש מאות רגלי, Ir hamotzia
chamesh me'ot ragli, a city that, it's an interesting phrase, that produces,
that comes out from it, 500 like foot
soldiers, what did that... not exactly clear what that means. Does that
mean it has a population of 500 people, or 500 men? ויצאו
ממנה, Veyatz'u mimena, again, המוציאה hamotzia and then ויצאו ממנה, veyatz'u mimena,
ג' מתים בג' ימים זה אחר זה. gimmel metim be-gimmel yamim zeh
achar zeh. So instead of the foot soldiers, people in their sort
of strength and virility, coming out of the city, instead you have
three dead people came out of the city. So anyway, it's a
city of a certain population. I think again, the imagery is רגלי
ragli as opposed to מתים. metim. But anyway, a city of a
certain size population, and there are three deaths בג' ימים זה אחר
זה be-gimmel yamim zeh achar zeh in three successive days. הרי זה
דבר. Harei zeh dever. That would be considered pestilence, that such a
high percentage is dying. פחות
מכאן, Pachot mikan, less than this, אין זה דבר, ein zeh dever,
it is
not considered to be pestilence. Presumably also if it was three day
after day but the city was larger, it also wouldn't be pestilence
because then it would be a lesser percentage. Percentage of the city.
So some way of measuring that there's a lot of deaths. Now
again, does that mean there's also signs that they see that they
identify with דבר, dever, certain physical signs on the body, fevers, or
whatever? And the question is together with that signs what makes it
rather than just a couple of freak deaths? You know, sort of
like what is that they have we have that whole thing what
is that the Center for CDC, right? How do you start when
do you start translating a couple of unexplained deaths into
a majority of its towns?
Right, there you go. A couple of unexplained deaths into describing it
as that we've actually got some communicable disease? Yeah, we've got some
and we've got some usual usual thing going on? And that seems
to be the issue. Presumably there are other indications that this wasn't
a guy that was ninety years old that died in his bed,
that there was some, you know, something unusual about these deaths. Yes,
Charlie.
I think this is the first example of the use of an
incidence rate in the history of epidemiology.
Oh, interesting. Mortality rate.
Very interesting. Okay. All right. Very good.
Okay. פחות מכאן אין זה דבר. pachot mikan ein zeh dever. על
אלו מתריעין. al elu matriyin. So those are the things that you
start immediately. So there's two חידושים we've been introduced to. Number one.
Number one is there's some things you start immediately. You have no
patience for it. It's not like the rain that will come a
little bit later. No, this thing is happening right away. We start
the end of the package immediately. Then there are others in which
it points that the חידוש chiddush is that it applies to a
it's immediately affecting a local region but the surrounding cities or villages
really is an עיר the surrounding villages also participate in a lesser
degree and the question is the lesser degree תענית taanit without תפילה
tefillah. or תפילה t’fillah. without תענית? taanit But that's this category two.
Now it continues. על אלו מתריעין בכל מקום. al elu matriyin bechol
makom. So within this context of the surrounding areas, the following are
things that are not just the surrounding areas but if they if
they occur in one place everywhere, everywhere like throughout the whole world
presumably. Everybody has to participate in the מתריעין matriyin and again presumably
מתריעין matriyin means the whole package. תענית ta’anit with the תפילה. tefilla,
What are they? על
השידפון ועל הירקון. al hashidafon ve'al hayerakon.
So שידפון shidafon is some type of a blight of the crops.
ירקון yerakon is jaundice and ועל הארבה ve'al haarbeh at least that's
what רש״י Rashi says here, right, presumably not about the crops, but
although it's funny that there would be that shift because the other
things are going to be very crop related. Does that say what
does that say for ירקון? yerakon? Does it say jaundice or does
it say a disease of the crops?
Yellowing, but of the crops, right, I assume it says? Yes, withering
and yellowing. Okay so we're still within the crops. Okay. So על
השידפון ועל הירקון al hashidafon ve'al hayerakon so either so
you know
right blight or or disease of the crops ועל ארבה ועל חסיל
ve'al arbeh ve'al chasil different types of
locusts.
ועל חסיל ve'al chasil is caterpillars.
Caterpillars. Interesting. So that's all crop related and then we shift to
and then we shift to things that apply that are about humans
and health and safety as we did before we were dealing with
issues like דבר. dever. ועל החיה הרעה ve'al hachaya hara'ah and like
you know wild animals, evil wild animals, it's interesting to to see
if how much any of these things parallel the ten מכות במצרים.
makkot bemitzrayim. You have דבר, dever, you have the the smiting of
the of the crops, you have the חיה הרעה. chaya hara'ah. Anyway,
ועל החיה הרעה ועל החרב ve'al hachaya hara'ah ve'al hacherev and about
you know troops, army troops that are going through and you know
conquering cities and marching through and wreaking violence. מתריעין עליה matriyin aleha
and in all those things everybody engages in the מתריעין matrin again
which presumably means the whole package, תענית ta’anit with the תפילות. מפני
שהיא מכה מהלכת. mipnei shehi makkah mehallechet. Because it is a plague,
it is that spreads, that's moving. It doesn't stay in one place,
right. If there's locusts, they'll wipe out one place and then they'll
move to the next. If there's these types of disease of the
crops, the disease spreads, the army troops spread. Now an interesting question
is number one, I if there's anything that I would think would
have been מהלכת mehallechet I would have said it would have been
the דבר dever of the previous category. So maybe they didn't exactly
know the con you know contagious
how contagious that was, maybe we don't exactly know what they meant
by דבר dever because obviously they understood the idea of contagion because
they're dealing with things like ירקון yerakon and they see that those
are issues that spread. Anyway these types of things are things that
apply to everybody that this thing could be coming to you next.
So even if troops are going through just the northern part...
yes now let's take a look, the משנה mishnah elaborates. Now again
the question is is there some point where you say no that's
never happening here? Right? You know? But but maybe not. Like maybe
it doesn't go from one continent to the next. But let's take
a look at what the משנה mishnah says.
Okay. מעשה maaseh where were we? שירדו זקנים מירושלים לעריהם sheyardu zekenim
miyerushalayim leareihem that the elders came from Jerusalem back to their villages
וגזרו
תענית על שנראה כמלא פי תנור שידפון באשקלון vegozeru taanit al she'nirka
kemlo pi tannur shidafon beashkelon and they made a תענית taanit because
there was the seen the fill of a oven we'll see what
that means of שידפון shidafon of this type of a you know
disease of the or destruction of the grain in אשקלון. Ashkelon. So
it’s not exactly clear, did they come from אשקלון Ashkelon to ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, or it sounds like they were in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, they heard
about what happened in אשקלון, Ashkelon, then when they went back to
their villages they made the תענית taanit in their villages as well
because of this, of this blasting of the grain in אשקלון. Ashkelon.
So that’s a pretty, okay, but it’s still all within, you know,
the bounds, all within Israel. It’s not so distance, but okay, so
what are the limits of בכל מקום? b’chol makom? So let’s keep
on going. ועוד גזרו תענית על שאכלו זאבים שני תינוקות לעבר הירדן
V’od gazru ta’anit al she’achlu ze’evim shnei tinokot l’ever ha’Yarden because a
wolf had, you know, had eaten two babies or two children in
עבר הירדן, Ever ha’Yarden, so there were these wild animals that were
attacking people in the settled areas. רבי יוסי אומר לא על שאכלו
אלא על שנראו. Rabbi Yose omer lo al she’achlu ela al shenir’u.
Not only, even if they didn’t attack yet, but the fact that
they were walking around in the, in the, you know, in the
settled areas, in the, in the villages and the cities and they’re
supposed to be only in the, you know, only in the forest,
so that itself is enough of a threat. Now again, that’s עבר
הירדן. Ever ha’Yarden. How far עבר הירדן? Ever ha’Yarden? עבר הירדן Ever
ha’Yarden is not חוץ לארץ. chutz la’aretz. Meaning even if they’re not
talking halachically עבר הירדן, Ever ha’Yarden, you know, עבר הירדן Ever ha’Yarden
still means in immediate proximity to Israel. It doesn’t mean way over
in בבל. Bavel. So what exactly is the limits of בכל מקום
b’chol makom is not clear. At a certain point, I mean, you
could ask it in two ways. Number one is to what degree
do you just feel a connectedness to, you know, do you sort
of see yourself as a, as belonging to that country or to
those people? You know, that’s like completely, even if in practice the
thing might spread, but it’s not שייך shayach to me, is sort
of the way you think, you know, to what degree is this
your country, your region? And the other question is the practical question.
At a certain point, you’ll say it’ll never possible that it’s going
to spread that far. Right? Something going on in Australia, right? I
mean, anything right now that we have all this massive communication, will
we be fasting everything? Because somewhere in the globe one of these
things is happening. So I think it’s a two question: it’s a
way of perception of connectedness and the reality of the concern of
it spreading. What are the limits of בכל מקום b’chol makom is
not, is not spelled out in this משנה. mishnah.
It’s a major difference with communication now. In other words, to have
a consciousness to get news out compared with any of the things
we assume today for communication. Right?
That news would spread, yeah, extraordinary. So I do and I do
think this raises, you know, a very important question because look, we’re
also getting into this issue of, you know, about that sense of
responsibility towards the rest of the community, you know, even a very
distantly spread community. So to some degree, and again also to this
question about why would the surrounding villages praying? You know, the רש"י
says they were praying because it might affect them as well. But
maybe they’re praying because they just have a responsibility, they have a
connectedness and they want to participate in the concern for this one
village among them even if it won’t affect them. Right? So I
think that there is a question here about that sense of responsibility,
although here we really do seem to be talking about impact. If
it's happening there, it’s going to happen to me. But still, it’s
a question of how do you perceive what you’re sort of, you
know, what your connectedness is, like, you know, who are not just
the people you’re relating to but sort of, you know, the country
that you’re in. You know, to what degree, I mean, we have
that problem as well that we tend to dismiss things, especially they
say like, you know, New Yorkers or in general or Americans, very
provincial. Right? Anything happening outside is completely not related to us. So,
you know, what are the parameters of that to the degree that,
again, both practically it might impact you, you know, people say no,
no, no, don’t dismiss what’s happening over there because that’s going to
impact our economy here. You know? And sometimes people acknowledge that and
sometimes they still dismiss it because it’s still not America, so who
cares. So, you know, I think there are those two issues: to
what degree will it actually have an impact and to what degree
do we perceive a sense of it relating to us? What are
the limits of בכל מקום? b’chol makom? Now again, that does this
also highlight the difference between the earlier case? The earlier case of
the, what do you call it, of the, of the raining only
on one city or the, you know, or the, or the דבר
או מפולת dever o mapolet only on one city means that there’s
really not such a concern that it’s going to spread. Right? It
only is going to be in that one local region. If it
was going to spread, then it would be, you would be doing
the full package in the surrounding cities. But you're right, the first
case, the first case, you only do the half the package, so
there it is assumed that it’s going to remain local. And even
though it’s going to remain local, nevertheless, the surrounding villages to some
degree participate in a lesser effect. But when there’s a real concern
that it’s going to spread and directly impact, then you do the
whole package, the תענית ta'anit, with the תפילה. tefilla. When it’s going
to remain local, but I’m surrounding and I’m nearby, then I participate
in a more partial way.
Is it then the troops in? Yeah, which is not going to,
I’m in America.
Well, that's the question. What's the limit of בכל מקום? b’chol makom?
I would, I presumably it's not, you know, there's some limits to
it. Okay, but still there’s still the difference between it spreading and
it might impact me, what are the limits of בכל מקום b’chol
makom as opposed to the earlier case where it wasn’t spreading but
it’s still happening to a local, to a place that’s nearby. What’s
my degree of participation and of caring about that when it’s nearby
but it’s not going to directly.
I find myself in a funny sort of argument for the empathy
side of the argument because you know as long as the event
doesn't spread, it actually is something where there's a regional economy that
serves the benefit of the people living around. Right, you mean the
fact that it raises prices go up. I sort of said that
sarcastically— I mean not sarcastically, but snidely before. Yes, it's true. Right?
Totally true. Right? So I think that thinking about the way we
really live, it has to be an empathetic response as opposed to—
Right, if it's not going to spread and it's not going to
impact me at all, then it's— yeah, I think I appreciate that.
Yeah. Okay. So now it says, so that is now three sections
we've got. Immediately, things that are impacted local won't spread, but the
way in which the surrounding villages have a partial participation, and things
that actually might spread and everybody has to go to the extreme.
The question I'm just raising is how far, what's the limits of
everybody?
What's the limits of כל מקום? kol makom? Now, fourth category. על
אלו מתריעין בשבת. Al elu matrin b'shabbat. Some things are so bad
that you even do it on שבת.
Shabbat. Now if מתריעין matrin means שופר shofar blasts, which is a
question, I mean you don't blow שופר shofar on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah on שבת, Shabbat, but okay. You know, maybe this is like
a real thing that's happening right now, פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. But
again, if it's a way of praying to God, right, so God
doesn't exactly need the שופר shofar blast. So let's take a look.
But maybe that's why the גמרא Gemara was inclined earlier to say
that מתריעין matrin does not mean שופר, shofar, מתריעין matrin means תפילות
because I couldn't imagine that you would blow the שופר shofar on
שבת. Shabbat. But על אלו מתריעין, al elu matrin,
but
these are the ones that you do these special תפילות with or
without שופר, shofar, but
you
do
the special תפילות
even
on
שבת. Shabbat. על עיר שהקיפוה נכרים, Al ir shehekifuah nochrim,
on a city that
is
surrounded by non-Jews and it's about to be like, you know, it's
being besieged. או נהר, O nahar, or a river that presumably is
about to
overflow. ועל הספינה המטורפת בים, V'al hasfina hamitorefet bayam, or on a
boat that's being tossed around in the sea that's caught up in
a storm. In all these things you would do it even on
שבת. Shabbat. Now, רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, לעזרה ולא לצעקה.
l'ezra v'lo l'tzeaka. Yes, you can do it on שבת Shabbat and
this might make more sense if you're dealing also with a שופר
shofar blast, but also verbally. But you can do it to call
people to aid. Right? So you can sound the alarm on שבת
Shabbat because these are things that, you know, people can come help
defend the city, help put the sandbags up for the overflowing river.
You know, I'm not exactly sure what the ספינה sfina is, maybe
send out other boats to try to, you know, rescue people. So
that you can do because— but not לצעקה, l'tzeaka, not to pray
to God. That's, you know, that wouldn't allow this to be— you
know, to do the מתריעין matri'in on שבת, Shabbat, which raises the
question, so for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi understand what's unique about these
cases. These cases not only is there a sense of like urgency
or emergency, I should say, but there could be an immediate human
response. So that's the idea of מתריעין אפילו בשבת. matrin afilu b'shabbat.
But according to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma if the תנא קמא
Tana Kamma is referring to praying to God, right, so what is
the idea of אפילו בשבת afilu b'shabbat uniquely here? Maybe also just
the degree of emergency is greater than all of these other things.
Like okay, there's a famine, there's all these things, there's these wolves,
but they're not the same sense of like every minute counts as
are the issue here about a river that's about to overflow or
a city that's about to be— you know, the walls of a
city are about to be breached. This is such a degree of
emergency that it's אפילו בשבת. afilu b'shabbat. Yes.
Yeah, but also the— you know, you can also make that same
distinction we were making over here as to how many other places
do it. If the river's going to overflow it may still go
downstream to you in your city— All
right, so that's another question as well. Fine, we're not combining those,
but
here we're focus— And if you're dry, like you know, if I'm
already in עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden, like I can't help them. Right?
Okay.
You're right. So the question also has to be asked about the
geographic region here, how this intersects with the earlier category. This does
not seem to be מהלך. mahalach. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like
this: שמעון התימני אומר אף על הדבר, Shimon HaTimni omer af al
hadever, שלא הודו לו חכמים. v'lo hodu lo Chachamim. Even about pestilence
you could cry out on שבת Shabbat and the sages did not
agree, which is interesting because in the context of the emergency, like
you know, and really understanding like I said, the CDC and what
communicable diseases could be, you understand like, yes, this— we bit— like
you gotta nip this in the bud as fast as possible. In
the— in the context of the possibility of human intervention, I don't
know what they thought you could do about
דבר. dever. Okay. על כל צרה שלא תבא על הצבור מתריעין עליהם,
Al kol tzara shelo tavo al hatzibur matrin aleihem, חוץ, chutz, on
any— on any affliction that should not come to the צבור, tzibur,
that's like a way of just being like, you know, like saying—
like קיין עין הרע— kein ayin hara like the opposite of קיין
עין הרע kein ayin hara or poopoo or whatever, like you know—
Not to mention— Right, exactly, shouldn't happen. But on any affliction מתריעין
matri'in עליהם, aleihem you do these full package of תענית ta'anit with
the תפילה, tefilla. חוץ מרוב גשמים. chutz mirov geshamim. The one thing
you would not do is too much rain. Too much rain, like
you don't— even though it's working out to your detriment, you don't
do this extreme sense of תענית and תפילות. for something that essentially
is a ברכה. bracha. We have enough of a hard time getting
sufficient rain. We're not going to make an overly big deal, even
when it's problematic, over too much rain. You know, we might do
some small things but we're not going to do this huge package
over too much rain. We should only have such problems. Okay, so
now we get the famous
story. מעשה ma'aseh story שאמרו לו לחוני המעגל, she-amru lo le-Choni Ha-Ma'agel,
they told Choni the circle drawer. There's a lot of interesting things
to say about this but I'll save it for when we revisit
this in the
גמרא. Gemara. I would just say the following that this is a
story that goes back to the period of the חשמונאים. Chashmonaim.
יוספוס Yosefus already records a story about חוני המעגל Choni Ha-Ma'agel and
the חשמונאים. Chashmonaim. Not this story, but a story that reflects the
fact that one of the brothers when the two brothers were warring
or
whatever, asked him to pray that the other side should lose, shouldn't
succeed. So
there was clearly a legend of this חוני המעגל Choni Ha-Ma'agel about
somebody whose תפילות were very effective and people would seek after him
in order to impact
the workings of or to get heaven to respond to what was
going down in the, here down on the earth. So here this
is being written about 300 years, and the point also mentioning is
that from the time of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim it's being recorded in
the משנה Mishna like 300 years from the time that he lived.
Yes. בלעם Bilam also had this.
Yeah, exactly, relevant to this week's פרשה. parsha. Right. Okay, so they
said to
חוני המעגל: Choni Ha-Ma'agel: התפלל שירדו גשמים, Hitpallel she-yerdu geshamim, pray that
the rains should come. Now what's interesting also to think about before
we continue for this story which I assume people know is at
what stage did they say this to him? Because just think about
the contrast. What has the משנה Mishna been telling us we're supposed
to be doing when there's no
rain? Right? תענית, תפילה. Right? At what stage did they go to
him? Like did they try to shortcut the whole thing and say,
oh let's not bother with all of that process, let's just get
חוני Choni to pray for us? Or maybe they tried the whole
series and it wasn't working and they're going to חוני Choni as
a last resort? Right? So it's an interesting gap, like when are
they going to חוני? Choni?
Or you've got two conflicting traditions of theological response. One is you
go to an ecstatic, to a special individual with magical powers who
will work, or you believe that the entire community, their moral fiber
is what God will respond to.
Right. That's a good and that's an excellent point. Like who were
the people that were going to
him? Right. And as we'll obviously see, this type of a power
in, as you say, an ecstatic or a charismatic individual is threatening
to the establishment power and institutionalized power. So
who were the people going to them, going to חוני? Choni? One
presumes that חז"ל Chazal would not have been happy with going to
חוני. Choni. And we'll see that at the end of the story.
So right, so could be both things were going on. Some people
are doing the תעניות and the whole thing as חז"ל Chazal wanted
and other people are saying let's just go to חוני Choni and
get him to work for us. So it's interesting to ask who's
going and when are they going to him. Okay, but they went
to
חוני המעגל Choni Ha-Ma'agel and התפלל שירדו גשמים, Hitpallel she-yerdu geshamim, pray
that rain should come. אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said
to them: צאו והכניסו תנורי פסחים בשביל שלא ימוקו. Tze'u ve-hakhnisu tannurei
psachim bishvil she-lo yimmoku. So חוני Choni was very confident about his
own abilities and he said: Go and bring in the ovens that
are used for roasting the פסחים psachim that they should not dissolve
because there's going to be so much rain. Now number one, it
has to rain a lot in order to dissolve pottery, I would
imagine. Number two, when is this
happening? Right? So if they've already brought their קרבן פסח, korban pesach,
then it's like in the middle of ניסן. Nissan. We learned before
that if it rains in ניסן Nissan it's a סימן קללה siman
kelala that the rain isn't doing any good once it's already ניסן.
Nissan. So maybe they're right at the towards the end of אדר.
Adar. And that's going to be a parallel version in the גמרא
Gemara is going to quote, it's going to be that it was
the end of אדר. Adar. So they're getting out their תנורי פסחים
tannurei psachim getting ready for פסח, Pesach, but it's not yet פסח.
Pesach. It's ממש mamash at the very, very end, at the last
minute. So if that's true, then at least it gives a little
context. It's like six months or five months since the middle of
מרחשון Marcheshvan we've been praying and fasting and גורנישט. gornisht. So now
at the very, very end as a last resort they're going to
חוני. Choni. So it's interesting how that might frame it in when
this is happening timewise. Let's just keep going.
Actually they had not had rain for almost a year by that
point.
Why a year?
Because there's no rain in the summer down
there.
Okay, good point. Okay, so now he's saying go and take in
the ovens so they shouldn't
dissolve. התפלל ולא ירדו גשמים. Hitpallel ve-lo yardu geshamim. Now he prayed
and maybe this is a little sense of a little 'serve him
right', you know, he was so overly confident. It didn't respond. Okay.
מה עשה? Mah asah? What did he do?
עג עוגה, Ag uga, he made a circle, ועמד בתוכה, ve-amad betokha,
and stood in the middle. ואמר לפניו, Ve-amar lefanav, and he said
to
Him, to God: רבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel olam, Master of the
Universe, בניך שמו פניהם עלי, banekha samu pneihem alay, Your children have
put their face towards me, שאני כבן בית לפניך, she-ani ke-ven bayit
lefanekha, that I'm like a member of the household before You. like
a member of your
household. נשבע אני בשמך הגדול, Nishba ani b'shimcha hagadol, I take an
oath in your great name, שאיני זז מכאן עד שתרחם על בניך,
She'eini zaz mikan ad sheterachem al banecha, that I will not move
from this circle until you have compassion on your children. התחילו, Hitchilu,
so obviously he has that sense of being able to demand and
his arrogance in his own abilities, I mean, it carries on even
at this stage through the תפילה. Although some do try to say
that בן בית ben bayit does not necessarily mean like a child
in a parent's house, but it means like a servant, like one
of the attendees, one of the people, the person who cooks and
cleans or who sweeps up, that's a בן בית. ben bayit. So
they have a little bit of a latitude, sort of like in
Shakespeare, it's the fool, the clown that always has a more of
a liberty to speak. So some want to say that that's like
what a בן בית ben bayit is. Somebody who's
a member of the household, not literally part of the family, but
somebody who's in the king's castle all the time. Anyway, that's right.
Anyway, that's interesting to wonder what בן בית ben bayit here, the
image of the בן בית. ben bayit. Okay, נשבע אני בשמך הגדול,
Nishba ani b'shimcha hagadol, oh we did that. Okay, התחילו גשמים מנטפים,
Hitchilu geshamim menatfin, so the rain started to drip, drizzle. אמר לא
כך שאלתי, Amar lo kach sha'alti, that wasn't what I asked for,
אלא גשמי בורות שיחין ומערות, ella gishmei borot sichin u'mearot,
enough rain to fill all of the wells and the cisterns. התחילו
לירד בזעף, Hitchilu layered beza'af, it started to come down in anger,
torrential. אמר לא כך שאלתי, Amar lo kach sha'alti,
that wasn't what I asked for, אלא גשמי
רצון, ella gishmei ratzon, rain of
desire, ברכה ונדבה, bracha u'nedava, blessing and giving. ירדו כתיקנן, Yardu ketiknan,
they fell down in the right way until עד שיצאו ישראל מירושלים
להר הבית, ad she'yatz'u Yisrael mi'Yerushalayim l'Har HaBayit, they had to abandon
their houses in ירושלים Yerushalayim and they all went up to הר
הבית Har HaBayit מפני הגשמים mipnei hageshamim
because of the rains. באו ואמרו לו, Ba'u v'amru lo, they came
and they said to him, כשם שהתפללת עליהם שירדו כך התפלל שילכו
להם, keshem shehitpallalta aleihem sheyerdu kach hitpallel sheyelchu lahem,
the same way you prayed they should come down, pray that they
should stop. אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said, צאו וראו אם נמחית
אבן הטועים. tze'u u're'u im nimcheta even hato'im.
Go see if the stone of the announcement stone has dissolved. There
was a stone in ירושלים Yerushalayim where basically they would stand up
and they would announce people that had lost
objects, so everybody when they would gather for the
רגלים regalim would be able to check out, it would be a
place of public announcements that people could find objects that they had
lost. So if that stone has dissolved, then then it's gotten to
be too much. So worn down by the rain, right. One wonders
what the bigger symbolism of that is. We can try to unpack
this a little bit more later.
Okay, but again notice, by the way, there's a certain sense here
about him getting
his arrogance sort of continuing. Like before he said
the ovens wouldn't dissolve and here it's like I'm only going to
stop it once the stone has worn away from the great rain.
Like he's not willing to be immediately responsive and he also anyway
but okay. So so that's the story. So what happened? שלח לו
שמעון בן
שטח, Shalach lo Shimon ben Shetach, so שמעון בן שטח, Shimon ben
Shetach, who was one of the leaders at that time, sent to
him, אלמלא חוני אתה, ilmalei Choni ata, if you were not חוני,
Choni, if you were not somebody that had such power, גוזרני עליך
נידוי, gozrani alecha nidui, I would put you in excommunication. אבל מה
אעשה לך שאתה מתחטא לפני המקום ועושה לך רצונך. aval ma e'eseh
lach she'ata mitchatei lifnei haMakom v'oseh lach retzonecha.
What should I do for you that you are מתחטא mitchatei before
God and God does your desires? Now מתחטא mitchatei is not exactly
clear what it means, but in another place רש״י Rashi explains it
means basically you misbehave. So you really are like a בן בית.
ben bayit. You're like a little kid, 'oh I want this', 'that's
not good enough', 'oh I want something else', 'that's not what I
asked for', 'I want something else'. One translates it as nag. You
nag.
I think misbehave. Okay, you misbehave, but you know what, God is
like a father, he has compassion on you כבן שמתחטא על אביו,
k'ven shemitchatei al aviv, which does make it sound like בן בית
ben bayit is more like literally the child, ועושה לו רצונו, v'oseh
lo retzono, that even when you misbehave, he's willing to go along.
ועליך הכתוב אומר v'alecha hakatuv omer ישמח אביך ואמך ותגל יולדתך, yismach
avicha v'imecha v'tagel yoladtecha, that your father will rejoice over you and
presumably even if you don't deserve it. Now it's a very strange
ending because God was not exactly being
עושה רצונו oseh retzono there, God was sort of technically responding but
obviously not happy and obviously
subverting. So when here when שמעון בן שטח Shimon ben Shetach is
trying to critique him, the fact that he sort of still says
that God does your desire
is a little funny. So there's obviously and one also imagines that
the חז״ל Chazal are trying to a little bit cut under his
power, his ability because that is threatening to the it's not just
the problem presumably one imagines the problem of חוני Choni was not
just that he was a little arrogant to God, so he's coming
to so this חרם cherem is coming to defend God's honor, how
could you be so disrespectful to God, but that also he was
a little bit threatening to rabbinic authority and part of this story
does undermine that, he thinks he has all these... powers, but in
the end he misbehaves and God isn't, you know, sometimes tolerates or
indulges but not, doesn't always really respond in the way that חוני
Choni thinks he's going to get a response.
That
some people have special relationships with God.
Yes, that certainly.
Yes, absolutely. You're right. I mean that they're not denying that he
had that, right, you know, because they can't. So that's interesting, meaning
the fact that there are people that have the power to pray,
but notice by the way earlier, right, that's a good question, earlier
when it spoke about the יחידים Yechidim praying or the זקן, Zaken,
those individuals who are always anonymous, and they were—and what put them
in that position was their character and their traits, not some ecstatic
ability. So, you know, now, so I do think that the idea
of חזל Chazal don't, you know, very much in understand why like
establishment authority doesn't want to acknowledge, you know, like this charismatic power
of a particular individual. So,
I think you're right that here they can't completely deny the reality
that everybody saw him as this wonder worker, so, but they're undercutting
it. So you're right, they could have just said, you know, you
don't have this ability, but I don't think that they could say
that. There was this perception that he did, but I think that
the story in many ways undercuts it. A) He misacts, B) God
doesn't really listen, he has this arrogance, it always might come to
be if might frustrate him, you know, work against him. So in
different ways they're undercutting it, but I don't think they're in a
position to completely deny it. But I think what's more—what's more interesting
is all the stuff we saw before, which is that the יחידים
Yechidim are anonymous, they're not people charismatic, you know, so I think
that's a really like—like being held up in contrast to this. Okay.
היו מתענין וירדו להם גשמים, Hayu mitanin ve-yardu lahem geshamim, so they
were fasting and then it started raining. So קודם, kodem, do they
continue fasting now that they've already started? So קודם הנץ החמה, kodem
hanetz hachamah, if they—if it was before sunrise, לא ישלימו, lo yashlimu,
don't finish your fast because they didn't really, the fast hasn't really,
you know, it's ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, it's now rain, and there's
no need to finish the fast, and you're not bound by it
yet. לאחר הנץ החמה, Le-achar hanetz hachamah, but if the fast was
already after sunrise, so now you've already defined the day as a
fast day, ישלימו, yashlimu, you have to finish fasting. So that becomes
fascinating, continuing to fast after your prayers are answered because of your
obligation of the fast. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, קודם חצות
לא ישלימו ולאחר חצות ישלימו. kodem chatzot lo yashlimu ve-le-achar chatzot yashlimu.
The difference is before and after חצות. chatzot. מעשה שגזרו תענית בלוד
וירדו להם גשמים קודם חצות, Ma’aseh she-gazru ta’anit be-Lod ve-yardu lahem geshamim
kodem chatzot, that they had a תענית and it rained before חצות.
chatzot. אמר להם רבי טרפון, Amar lahem Rabbi Tarfon, צאו ואכלו ושתו
ועשו יום טוב. Tze’u ve-ichlu u-she’tu ve-asu yom tov. Go out, eat,
drink, make a יום טוב. yom tov. ויצאו ואכלו ושתו ועשו יום
טוב ובאו בין הערבים וקראו הלל הגדול. Veyatz’u ve-ichlu u-she’tu ve-asu yom
tov u-bau bein ha-arbayim ve-kar’u Hallel HaGadol. And they even came back
for בין הערבים bein ha-arbayim and they read הלל. Hallel. הלל הגדול
Hallel HaGadol is not what we call הלל. Hallel. What we call
הלל Hallel is הלל המצרי. Hallel HaMitzri. הלל הגדול Hallel HaGadol is
the—what we add into the פסוקי דזמרה Pesukei d'Zimra on שבת, Shabbat,
the extra הודו לה' כי טוב. Hodu la-Hashem ki tov. Right. Okay.
Anyway,
so that is very interesting, but again, you know, what this also
sort of does bring up is it brings up the almost institutionalized
nature of a fast as opposed to the immediacy of the relationship
of the previous story. Right? The previous story, חוני Choni was praying,
God was answering, you know, there was this immediacy of the relationship.
If you think about, I'm fasting and I'm praying and then God
brings down the rain, so what do I do? I say thank
you and I stop fasting and I stop דאווענינג. davening. The possibility
that you continue to fast even after you've been answered because, well,
technically you've already turned it into a fast day so you have
to finish your fast, you know, again sort of brings it to
the sort of more formal and institutional nature of the practice, you
know, beyond that just immediate sort of, you know, dynamic with God
and the immediacy of the responsiveness and the relationship. Okay. משנה. Mishnah.
גמרא. Gemara. סדר תעניות אלו אמרו ברביעה ראשונה. Seder ta’aniyot elu amru
bi-revi’ah rishonah. ורמינהו. U-reminhu. רביעה ראשונה ושניה לשאול, שלישית להתענות. Revi’ah rishonah
u-shniyah lish’ol, shlishit lehit’anot.
You know, only if the first and the second dates that are
passed when it should have rained, you're still just praying. You only
begin fasting when it passes the third date. You know, the whole
question earlier, when does it, at what stage do you start fasting?
So אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, הכי קאמר. hachi ka-amar.
So here's what it means when the משנה Mishnah says the first
רביעה ראשונה revi’ah rishonah you're fasting. סדר תעניות האמור אימתי. Seder ta’aniyot
ha-amur eimatai. The normal order of the three, three, and seven, when
is that? בזמן שיצאה רביעה ראשונה ושניה ושלישית ולא ירדו גשמים. Be-zman
she-yatz’ah revi’ah rishonah u-shniyah u-shlishit ve-lo yardu geshamim.
It means not when the first date has been passed. It means
when the first rain has been delayed, the—delayed beyond the first date
and the second date and the third date. Now that that first
rain has been delayed until the third date and still hasn't rained,
now we're going to fast. אבל ירדו גשמים ברביעה ראשונה, Aval yardu
geshamim bi-revi’ah rishonah,
but if the rain came on the first date when it should
have come, וזרעו ולא צמחו, ve-zar’u ve-lo tzamchu, and they planted and
the things did not spring, אי נמי צמחו וחזרו ונשתנו, i nami
tzamchu ve-chazru ve-nishtanu, or they sprang but then they—they changed in some
type of a form, there was some type of a disease in
them, then מתריעין עליהם aleihem מיד. Then you do it immediately. Even
if it's before that date of the third date that had passed.
past. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, דוקא davka נשתנו, nishtanu, only
if they have actually undergone some type of a change, אבל יבשו
yavshu לא, dried out, not. Now, not what is a little unclear,
there's two readings of this. One reading is if they dried out,
you don't have to fast because that'll recover by itself. The other
answer is,
the other explanation is don't bother doing the תפילות, תפילות aren't going
to help, if they're already dry, it's done with. But תוספות Tosafot
prefers the second read, the first read, which is if they're dry,
it's not so bad, they could recover. גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, peshita,
obviously נשתנו תנן, nishtanu tenan, it says if they changed. No, לא
צריכא דאקו. lo tzericha de'aku. So the case is is that not
only have they dried, but now they've a little bit like
fixed or it's a little question what that means, but they're a
little bit recovered. מהו דתימא אקנתא מילתא היא, mahu deteima akanta milta
hee, now maybe this fact that they are a little recovered, they
dried and they recovered, but they haven't again, the way תוספות Tosafot
reads it, they haven't fully progressed, so maybe that really shows that
they're like stuck in this mode, you know, like that they're that
so now maybe actually they need the תפילות because now they're starting
to recover, if you don't get the תפילות then it won't finish
and it'll be it'll go to waste, קא משמע לן ka mashma
lan not that way. Okay, so dried out again, it's a little
hard to read it either way. The other way to read it
maybe which is easier is that if it's dried out you don't
bother praying because it's not going to do any good. And then
the הוה אמינא hava amina makes more sense. No, maybe if it
actually seems to start to recover a little bit, we should pray
for it, it will do some good. And the answer is no,
that's not really significant and if it really did dry out then
forget about it, they're wasted anyway. Okay, וכן שפסקו שמים בין גשם
לגשם, vechen shepas'ku shamayim bein geshem legeshem, if there's a forty day
gap between rains. מאי מכת בצורת? mai makat batzoret? What's this מכת
בצורת? makat batzoret? So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav, right, which is in those things that you're מתריעין עליהם
מיד, right, so says אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav,
בכא baka המביאה hamevi'ah לידי lidei בצורת, batzoret, a type of a
type of a, you know, plague or some type of a thing
that is going to lead to insufficient grain. So whatever it is,
presumably it's rain related.
But some type of a thing that's going to lead to insufficient
grain. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, נהרא אנהרא בצורתא. nahara anahera
batzorta. If you can travel by river to
get grain from another locale, from like a neighboring village, then it's
only considered בצורת. batzoret. It's not yet fully at the full stage
of tragedy. מדינתא אמדינתא כפנא, medinta amedinta kafna, if you have to
go from one country to another country
to get grain, כפנא, kafna, that's a real famine. So כפנא kafna
is the Aramaic of the word רעב, ra'av, ויהי רעב בארץ, vayehi
ra'av ba'aretz, right when אברהם Avraham goes down to מצרים, Mitzrayim, the
Aramaic is כפנא, kafna, not בצורתא. batzorta. So there you have to
travel to another country. That's already the state of רעב, ra'av, of
כפנא. kafna. ואמר רבי חנינא, V'amar Rabbi Chanina, סאה בסלע ושכיחא, se'ah
besela ush'chicha, let's say a סאה se'ah of grain cost a סלע,
sela, which is very expensive. Okay, but nevertheless, even if it's expensive,
if there's a lot of grain to be had in the market,
so then בצורתא, batzorta, that's a בצורת. batzoret. So it's high inflation,
so it's very expensive, but it's very available. So that's only the
בצורת batzoret which is not the full degree of severity. ארבעה ולא
שכיחא, arba'a velo sh'chicha, if you can get four סאה se'ah for
סלע, sela, it's cheap, but but it's not you can't find it
anywhere. Sure, if you can find it, it's cheap, but nobody has
it, everybody is out of it. So in that case כפנא, kafna,
in that case it's much worse, it's not about the price, it's
about the availability. Again, if somebody maybe David who's I see you're
leaving could explain to us, but I don't understand how you could
have something that's a rare commodity that everybody needs that remains cheap.
Okay, but that's what he's saying. If somehow the prices haven't adjusted
yet and technically it's cheap but nobody is selling it, then it's
considered a רעב. ra'av. ואמר רבי יוחנן, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan, לא שנו
אלא בזמן שמעות בזול ופירות ביוקר. lo shanu ela bizman shema'ot bezol
uperot beyoker. All of this is true if money is cheap, what
means money is cheap but anyway, people you know money is available
and the fruits and and the food is expensive. And then we
can say, you know, it could be expensive but if it's if
it's if it's available, it's still not considered to be a רעב.
ra'av.
Ireland had plenty of
food they had to export it.
And a million people starved to death.
Why? It was all export. Oh. Okay,
אבל
מעות ביוקר, aval ma'ot beyoker, wait a minute, cheap maybe is inflation,
well
right presumably it means right, אבל מעות ביוקר aval ma'ot beyoker if
it's very rare to have money ופירות בזול uperot bezol and the
fruit is cheap, so מתריעין עליהם מיד. Then you blow, then you
immediately begin the severe fast. So everything is selling for a dollar,
but nobody has any money, right? Nobody even has a dollar, people
you know people have a few pennies. So even though it's so
cheap, it's only a dollar, but what really is is that the
not that the prices of the grain have gone up, the prices
of the grain might still be low, but no but nobody has
any money. In that case that's that's terrible. ואמר רבי יוחנן, V'amar
Rabbi Yochanan, נהירנא nehirna I remember, כד הוה קיימי ארבע סאין בסלע,
kad havah kaimei arba se'in besela, where you'd get four סאה se'ah
for סלע, sela, it was dirt cheap, והוו נפישי נפישי כפנא, v'avu
nefishei nefishei kafna, but... There was a great profusion of people that
were that were like נפיחי כפן nefichei kafan means people that were
bloated because of famine, right? That happens during famine. Why? Because נפיחי
כפן nefichei kafan בטבריא b'Tveria means לית עיסא leis isa because nobody
could even put their put you know had a penny to spend.
Now I do not understand and somebody could explain to me what
difference does it make if the reason the stuff is not available
is because it's very expensive or the reason it's not available is
because technically the price might be cheap but nobody has but nobody
has any money? Like what difference does it make?
Yeah, I'm not getting something here. I got the first point that
it's not about the price, it's about the availability, that that makes
a huge difference, but I don't exactly get the point here where
where a high price is not so bad but a low price
that nobody has any money, that's worse. Like, I'm not exactly getting
it. All right. ירדו לצמחים אבל לא לאילן, yardu l'tzmachim aval lo
l'ilan, try to get a little bit further. בשלמא לצמחים ולא לאילן
משכחת לה דאתי ניחא ולא אתי
רזיא, bishlama l'tzmachim v'lo l'ilan mashkachat lah d'atei nicha v'lo atei razya,
so it's good for the crops and not the trees if it
comes down pleasantly and not strongly. לאילן ולא לצמחים דאתי רזיא ולא
אתי ניחא, l'ilan v'lo l'tzmachim d'atei razya v'lo atei nicha,
it's good for the trees and not the crops if it's strong
but it's not like pleasant rain. לזה ולזה ולא לבורות לשיחין ולמערות
l'zeh v'l'zeh v'lo l'borot l'shichin u'l'm'arot
and good for the trees and the and the crops but not
for the wells משכחת לה דאתי רזיא וניחא מיהו טובא לא אתי,
mashkachat lah d'atei razya v'nicha mihu tuba lo atei, you have some
that's sort of pleasant, that's you know some that's strong,
a lot doesn't come, it doesn't fill up the wells. אלא הא
דתניא ירדו לבורות לשיחין ולמערות אבל לא לזה ולזה, ela ha d'tanya
yardu l'borot l'shichin u'l'm'arot aval lo l'zeh v'l'zeh, but we have a
ברייתא braita that has a fourth category: it fills up the wells
but not for the trees or the crops. היכי משכחת לה, heichi
mashkachat lah, how does that happen? דאתי בשפיכותא d'atei b'shfichuta
because it comes in in torrents. So a little hard is good
for the rains, but torrents, it'll fill up the wells but it's
not good for anything. תנו רבנן מטריעין
על האילנות בפרוס הפסח, tanu rabanan matri'in al ha'ilanot b'fros haPesach, you
make the fasts for the trees in half of Pesach, meaning half
a month before Pesach, on ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan is
when you start worrying about the trees if it's not raining, which
is interesting, right? Because right we've always been focusing on the crops
and in מרחשון. Marcheshvan. Here the trees, although ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shvat
came earlier, but presumably the trees start needing water you know by
middle you know towards the springtime, so by ניסן Nissan if it
hasn't rained, right, again maybe two months or whatever after ט"ו בשבט,
Tu B'Shvat, by ניסן Nissan if it hasn't rained you start you
start this for the trees. A new a new time on the
calendar when to start worrying about rain. הבורות והשיחין והמערות אפילו בפרוס
החג. haboorot v'hashichin v'ham'arot afilu b'fros hachag. Now the wells even ראש
חודש תשרי Rosh Chodesh Tishrei you have you know you need it
to start raining to fill up the wells, which is funny. Was
it the time yet of rain? Is it because people are expecting
the עולי רגלים olei regalim and they're going to need water in
their wells? What is it about ראש חודש תשרי Rosh Chodesh Tishrei
that already you were expecting enough rain to fill up the wells?
I really don't get all of this. ועל כולם אם אין להם
מים לשתות v'al kulam im ein lahem mayim lishtot and for anybody
for all times if you're running out of drinking water, not just
that you don't have enough water to fill up the wells, you
don't have drinking water, מטריעין עליהם מיד, matri'in aleihem miyad, then you
respond immediately. ואיזו היא מיד שלהם שני וחמישי ושני. v'eizu hi miyad
shelahem sheni v'chamishi v'sheni. What does the מיד mean? Monday, Thursday, Monday,
meaning what's the response. Now presumably is what that means. It's not
like a seven-day period that you respond, it's a three-day. It's an
interesting though way of framing it. ועל כולם אין מטריעין עליהם אלא
באפרכיא שלהם. v'al kulam ein matri'in aleihem ela b'aprachya shelahem. And again,
as opposed to some of the other cases in the משנה, mishna,
all of these would only be in their region, not in another
region. אסכרה, askara, and אסכרה askara which was
what do they think that as diphtheria?
I thought
they said it was croup. What is it?
Diphtheria? I thought they said it was croup, croup, anybody know about
this? No. Sally?
Croup could be it, right?
I don't know. Okay. Anyway, it was something that was a terrible
a terribly you know painful disease and caused death and got and
sort of invaded through the throat. So for this אסכרה, askara, בזמן
שיש בה מיתה, bizman sheyesh bah mita, as it led to death,
מטריעין עליה, matri'in aleiha, then you have this response. ובזמן שאין בה
מיתה, uvizman she'ein bah mita, if it does not lead to lead
to death, אין מטריעין עליה. ein matri'in aleiha. So again one wonders
if people understood whether it was contagious or not, but it's also
interesting that if it's just people are getting sick, even a contagious
disease, it need it's not maybe severe enough to have this type
of a response. ומטריעין על הגובאי בכל שהוא, umatri'in al hagovai b'chol
shehu, and if it's גובאי govai which are a type of a
what do you call it? A locust, then even a small amount
because you don't just have one locust. If you're going to get
a locust, it's going to you're going to get a lot. רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר אומר אף על החגב, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer
af al hachagav, which is another type of a you know not
grasshopper, those sound innocent, but whatever it is, another type of a
locust. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, we'll just do one more, מטריעין על
האילנות בשאר שני שבוע, matri'in al ha'ilanot b'shar shenei shavua, you pray
for the trees if there's a you know if. Because if there's
a problem with the rain on all of the other years of
the שמיטה Shmita cycle but not on שמיטה Shmita itself, because on
שמיטה Shmita you know people aren't harvesting the stuff. Of course תוספות
Tosafot makes the opposite argument, שמיטה Shmita is when you need there
to be fruit on the trees. אבל על
השיתין ועל המרסות אפילו בשביעית. aval al hashitin v'al hamarsot afilu bishvi'it.
רבן שמעון גמליאל אומר: Rabban Shimon Gamliel omer: אף על האילנות בשביעית
af al hailanot bishvi'it מפני שיש בה פרנסה לעניים. mipnei sheyesh ba
parnasa la'aniyim.
Even for the trees because what are the poor going to eat?
They need there to be crops in the ground, that's part of
the whole idea of שמיטה. Shmita. So of course you need it
to rain on שמיטה Shmita so that there should be fruit on
the trees. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, one wonders what the תנא
קמא was thinking. מתריעין על האילנות, matri'in al hailanot, maybe because he
figured maybe everybody had stored up food for שמיטה. Shmita. מתריעין על
האילנות בשאר שני השבוע, matri'in al hailanot bish'ar shnei hashavua, על השיתין
ועל המרסות אפילו בשביעית. al hashitin v'al hamarsot afilu bishvi'it. רבן שמעון
גמליאל אומר: Rabban Shimon Gamliel omer: אף על האילנות מתריעין, af al
hailanot matri'in, even for the trees, על הספיחין בשביעית, al hasifichin bishvi'it,
מתריעין אף על האילנות, matri'in af al hailanot, period, even on the
trees. מתריעין על הספיחין בשביעית מפני שיש בהן פרנסה
לעניים. matri'in al hasifichin bishvi'it mipnei sheyesh bahen parnasa la'aniyim. So and
it's a little bit
where were we? It seems like the same thing
except the question about the ספיחין. sifichin. ספיחין sifichin are also things
that grow a little bit like randomly. The way רש״י Rashi reads
it: אף על האילנות ואף על הספיחין. af al hailanot v'af al
hasifichin. ספיחין sifichin are things like the trees, not only fruits that
grow from the trees, but also like wild vegetation that grows without
being planted. So not just for the trees, but even for other
wild vegetation that will grow on שביעית shvi'it that the עניים aniyim
need. There's a whole question about whether you're allowed to eat this
ספיחין sifichin or not. Okay, I think
we will have to end here. We'll pick up from there tomorrow.